<Jokes>
  <GoodJokes>
    <Joke>
      <Text>This shutdown is bad for everyone in the service industry, but it especially sucks for men
We're losing $1 for every $.79 women are losing</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>Scientist: "My findings are meaningless if taken out of context."
Media: Scientist claims "Findings are meaningless."</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>All countries eventually got coronavirus
But China got it right off the bat.</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>An infinite number of mathematicians walk into a bar
The first mathematician orders a beer
The second orders half a beer
"I don't serve half-beers" the bartender replies
"Excuse me?" Asks mathematician #2
"What kind of bar serves half-beers?" The bartender remarks. "That's ridiculous."
"Oh c'mon" says mathematician #1 "do you know how hard it is to collect an infinite number of us? Just play along"
"There are very strict laws on how I can serve drinks. I couldn't serve you half a beer even if I wanted to."
"But that's not a problem" mathematician #3 chimes in "at the end of the joke you serve us a whole number of beers. You see, when you take the sum of a continuously halving function-"
"I know how limits work" interjects the bartender
"Oh, alright then. I didn't want to assume a bartender would be familiar with such advanced mathematics"
"ARE YOU KIDDING ME?" The bartender replies, "you learn limits in like, 9th grade! What kind of mathematician thinks limits are advanced mathematics?"
"HE'S ON TO US" mathematician #1 screeches
Simultaneously, every mathematician opens their mouth and out pours a cloud of multicolored mosquitoes. Each mathematician is bellowing insects of a different shade.
The mosquitoes form into a singular, polychromatic swarm. "FOOLS" it booms in unison, "I WILL INFECT EVERY BEING ON THIS PATHETIC PLANET WITH MALARIA"
The bartender stands fearless against the technicolor hoard. "But wait" he interrupts, thinking fast, "if you do that, politicians will use the catastrophe as an excuse to implement free healthcare. Think of how much that will hurt the taxpayers!"
The mosquitoes fall silent for a brief moment. "My God, you're right. We didn't think about the economy! Very well, we will not attack this dimension. FOR THE TAXPAYERS!" and with that, they vanish.
A nearby barfly stumbles over to the bartender. "How did you know that that would work?"
"It's simple really" the bartender says. "I saw that the vectors formed a gradient, and therefore must be conservative."</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>A vagrant, finding no place on the pavement, parked himself at the feet of a statue of Mahatma Gandhi. At midnight he was woken up by someone gently tapping him with his stick. It was the Mahatma himself. ‘You Indians have been unfair to me,’ complained the benign spirit. "You put my statues everywhere that show me either standing or walking. My feet are very tired. Why can’t I have a horse like the one Chhatrapati Shivaji (an Indian king) has? Surely, I did as much for the nation as he! And you still call me your Bapu (father)."
Next morning the vagrant went round calling on the ministers. At long last he persuaded one to join him for a night-long vigil at the feet of the Mahatma’s statue. Lo and behold, as the neighboring police station gong struck the midnight hour, the Mahatma emerged from his statue to converse with the vagrant. He repeated his complaint of having to stand or walk and his request to be provided a mount like the Chhatrapati.
"Bapu,’ replied the vagrant, "I am too poor to buy you a horse, but I have brought this minister from the Government for you. He …" Bapu looked at the minister and remarked: "I asked for a horse, not a donkey."</Text>
    </Joke>
  </GoodJokes>
  <BadJokes>
    <Joke>
      <Text>Why did the chicken cross the road? Because it wanted to get to the other side.</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>I’m reading a book on anti-gravity. It’s impossible to put down. Haha.</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>Knock knock. Who's there? Boo. Boo who? Don’t cry, it’s just a joke.</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>What did one wall say to the other wall? I'll meet you at the corner.</Text>
    </Joke>
    <Joke>
      <Text>My dog used to chase people on a bike a lot. It got so bad, finally I had to take his bike away.</Text>
    </Joke>
  </BadJokes>
</Jokes>
