
  <Criteria name="Mechanism">
    <Category name="Wordplay / Puns">
      <Factor name="Linguistic Creativity">
        <Explanation>
          Creativity in the manipulation of language—unexpected usage of words, idioms, homophones, or syntax.
          A good pun surprises and delights by revealing a clever dual meaning.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "I used to be a banker but I lost interest."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "Time flies like an arrow. Fruit flies like a banana." (overused, lacks freshness)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Sound/Meaning Play">
        <Explanation>
          Uses similar-sounding words or homonyms to create a humorous double meaning.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "A bicycle can't stand on its own because it's two-tired."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "I’m on a seafood diet. I see food and I eat it." (predictable, cliché)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Malapropisms">
      <Factor name="Misused Precision">
        <Explanation>
          Humor from the misuse of a word that sounds similar but has a completely different meaning. Works best when context amplifies the absurdity.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "We cannot let terrorists and rogue nations hold this nation hostile."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "I might just evaporate to another city." (confusing rather than funny)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Contextual Contrast">
        <Explanation>
          The mistaken word must clearly contrast with the intended one in a way that generates absurd or ironic meaning.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Texas has a lot of electrical votes." (electoral → electrical)
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "He’s a vast suppository of information." (Funny once, but tired now)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Non-sequiturs">
      <Factor name="Surprise Value">
        <Explanation>
          The punchline diverges unexpectedly from the setup in a nonsensical or unrelated way, often creating humor from absurdity.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "I asked my dog what’s two minus two. He said nothing."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "I like cereal. The sky is blue." (Random but not witty)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Absurd Coherence">
        <Explanation>
          Despite illogical progression, there's a thread of humorous pseudo-logic.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Time is a flat circle. Pancakes prove it."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "My computer is made of fish. Don’t eat my shoes." (Too random)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Irony / Sarcasm">
      <Factor name="Tone Control">
        <Explanation>
          The joke must deliver a contrast between the literal statement and its implied meaning through tone or context.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Great, another rainy day. I just love ruining my new suede shoes."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "Oh joy, my flight’s delayed!" (Blunt, lacks finesse)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Contextual Awareness">
        <Explanation>
          The sarcasm should depend on shared knowledge or situations to land effectively.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Of course I trust the politician. Just like I trust my cat with my lasagna."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "Nice going, Einstein." (Too generic, lacks context)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Absurdity / Surrealism">
      <Factor name="Imaginative Leap">
        <Explanation>
          Humor from breaking reality in creative or whimsical ways.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "I poured root beer into a square cup. Now I just have beer."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "My head is a fishbowl filled with screams." (Too abstract without structure)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Controlled Nonsense">
        <Explanation>
          The nonsense should be contained within a setup/punchline structure to avoid chaos.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "If life gives you melons, you might be dyslexic."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "The ceiling is bread. I walk to the moon with my beard." (Unstructured randomness)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Double Entendres">
      <Factor name="Layered Meaning">
        <Explanation>
          The joke should deliver a clean interpretation and a risqué or clever second meaning.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Marriage is a fine institution, but I’m not ready for an institution."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "She’s a smart cookie, and I’d like a bite." (Too direct, lacks subtlety)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Subtle Suggestiveness">
        <Explanation>
          The humor works best when it skirts the edge of inappropriateness without being crude.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Is that a banana in your pocket, or are you just happy to see me?"
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "Wanna come over and study anatomy?" (Blunt, no finesse)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Misdirection">
      <Factor name="Expectation Subversion">
        <Explanation>
          Leads the audience to expect one punchline and delivers a surprise instead.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "I have the heart of a lion… and a lifetime ban from the zoo."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "My wife left me… but now I can finally sleep on the couch." (Weak twist)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Logical Pivot">
        <Explanation>
          A believable narrative or premise shifts logically to an absurd or unexpected conclusion.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "I threw a boomerang a few years ago. I now live in constant fear."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "I was hungry, so I bought a hat." (Pivot lacks logic or payoff)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Self-referential / Meta-humor">
      <Factor name="Humor Awareness">
        <Explanation>
          The joke demonstrates self-awareness about its own construction or joke-telling mechanics.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "This joke works on so many levels, it’s basically an elevator."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "This is a joke. Laugh now." (Too literal)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Structural Playfulness">
        <Explanation>
          It creatively manipulates the structure or delivery of traditional jokes.
        </Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "Why did the chicken cross the road? To subvert your expectations."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "Knock knock. Who’s there? Me. Me who? Me doing this badly." (Low payoff)
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>
  </Criteria>
  
  
  
  
  
  
	<Criteria name="Theme">
	  <Category name="Animals">
		<Factor name="Linguistic Creativity">
		  <Explanation>How creatively language is used to describe animal behaviors, traits, or scenarios.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why don't seagulls fly over the bay? Because then they'd be bagels."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Cows go moo. That's funny, right?"</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Personification">
		  <Explanation>Giving animals human-like traits to create humor or satire.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"My dog thinks he’s human. He even yells at Alexa."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"The cat was sitting. Like a person. Hilarious?"</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Politics">
		<Factor name="Sharp Commentary">
		  <Explanation>Effectively critiquing political ideologies, figures, or policies with wit.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Politicians and diapers should be changed often—both for the same reason."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"I don't like politicians. They're dumb."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Topical Relevance">
		  <Explanation>Refers to how well the joke aligns with current political events or discourse.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Inflation is so bad, my Monopoly money is now worth more than my paycheck."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"I heard a joke about the Berlin Wall. Topical, right?"</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Religion">
		<Factor name="Fairness">
		  <Explanation>Respectful tone while making light-hearted observations on religious practices or beliefs.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I have a lot of respect for monks. I mean, they take a vow of silence and still put up with group chats."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"All religious people are dumb." (offensive, lacks wit)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Symbolic Subversion">
		  <Explanation>Using religious symbols or stories in a surprising or humorous context.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Moses had the first tablet that could connect to the cloud."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Jesus walked on water. Cool. Anyway..."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Sex / Adult">
		<Factor name="Double Entendre Cleverness">
		  <Explanation>Wit in using ambiguous or layered language that can be interpreted innocently or sexually.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I told her she had a beautiful chassis. Turns out she wasn’t into car metaphors."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Boobs are funny." (Too direct and lacks sophistication)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Balance of Crudeness and Wit">
		  <Explanation>How well the joke balances mature content with cleverness rather than shock value alone.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Love is blind, but marriage is a real eye-opener."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Sex is gross. Haha." (Low effort, no wit)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Workplace">
		<Factor name="Relatability">
		  <Explanation>Capturing common workplace scenarios in a humorous way that resonates widely.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I pretend to work as they pretend to pay me."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Office chairs roll. That’s it."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Sarcastic Tone">
		  <Explanation>Using dry or sarcastic humor to point out workplace absurdities.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Teamwork is important—it gives you someone to blame."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"My boss exists. So funny, right?"</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Relationships / Marriage">
		<Factor name="Punch Impact">
		  <Explanation>Strong, memorable endings that twist typical relationship dynamics.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"My wife and I were happy for twenty years—then we met."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Marriage is a thing. It exists."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Observational Accuracy">
		  <Explanation>Sharp, funny takes on real quirks of relationships.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Marriage is finding that one special person to annoy for a lifetime."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Relationships are just confusing." (Vague and unoriginal)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Children / Parenting">
		<Factor name="Innocent Irony">
		  <Explanation>Humor from children's literal logic or parental chaos, without being mean-spirited.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Kids: they dance like no one's watching. But they also scream like everyone's deaf."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"My kid is dumb." (Cruel, not funny)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Role Reversal Humor">
		  <Explanation>Placing adults in child-like roles or vice versa for comedic effect.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Parenting is just saying 'because I said so' until you die."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Kids cry a lot." (Obvious, not insightful)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="School / Exams / Students">
		<Factor name="Academic Irony">
		  <Explanation>Making fun of the paradoxes or uselessness in educational systems.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why do I need math? I have a calculator and anxiety."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"School is boring." (Unoriginal, too broad)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Relatable Stress">
		  <Explanation>Highlighting shared academic struggles humorously.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Final exams: the reason coffee and panic attacks became best friends."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Homework is hard." (Too bland)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Ethnicity / Nationality / Stereotypes">
		<Factor name="Cultural Nuance">
		  <Explanation>Capturing quirks or differences with wit and sensitivity, not mockery.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"In Italy, even the GPS has an accent. 'In 500 meters, you-a turn-a left!'"</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Germans have no humor." (Flat, offensive)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Avoiding Punching Down">
		  <Explanation>The joke should not target marginalized groups for easy laughs.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Americans think a kilometer is a communist conspiracy."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Mexicans are lazy. Haha." (Offensive, not funny)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Technology / IT / Programming">
		<Factor name="Inside Knowledge Fun">
		  <Explanation>Rewards tech-savvy audiences with clever, accurate humor.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why do programmers prefer dark mode? Because light attracts bugs."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Computers are weird." (Generic)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Syntax Humor">
		  <Explanation>Plays with code, logic, or programming language syntax.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I would love to change the world, but they won’t give me the source code."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"C++ is stupid." (Rant, not a joke)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Science / Math / Academia">
		<Factor name="Conceptual Wit">
		  <Explanation>Applies scientific or mathematical ideas in unexpected but logical ways.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Parallel lines have so much in common. It’s a shame they’ll never meet."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Math is hard. I hate it." (Not humorous or clever)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Interdisciplinary Play">
		  <Explanation>Combines fields (e.g., physics + philosophy) for intellectual humor.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Schrödinger’s cat walks into a bar. Or does it?"</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Einstein was smart. LOL." (No depth or play)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Dark / Morbid humor">
		<Factor name="Shock with Substance">
		  <Explanation>Startles the audience, but has a clever or cathartic point.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I have a friend who’s a suicide prevention counselor... He’s hanging in there."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Death is funny." (No structure or insight)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Emotional Subversion">
		  <Explanation>Twists serious emotional subjects in a surprising yet meaningful way.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"My therapist said I should do what makes me happy. So I’m eating cake in the dark."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Orphans are funny. Haha." (Insensitive, cruel)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Pop Culture / Celebrity">
		<Factor name="Name Play and Mimicry">
		  <Explanation>Imitating or punning on celebrity names or behaviors cleverly.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Kanye West’s ego is the only thing faster than Wi-Fi."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Celebrities are dumb." (Generic insult)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Topical Twist">
		  <Explanation>Relating trending events or gossip to universal situations in a clever way.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Taylor Swift has more breakups than my Wi-Fi connection."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Justin Bieber is weird." (No creative spin)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Historical / Intellectual humor">
		<Factor name="Clever Anachronism">
		  <Explanation>Places historical figures in modern scenarios or mixes eras unexpectedly.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Julius Caesar’s final words: ‘Et tu, Bluetooth?’"</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"History is old. LOL." (Lazy humor)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Reference Density">
		  <Explanation>Layers of references or accurate intellectual allusions that reward deep knowledge.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Descartes walks into a bar. Bartender asks, 'Want a beer?' Descartes says, 'I think not'—and disappears."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Philosophy is dumb." (No engagement or understanding)</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>
	</Criteria>








  <Criteria name="Structure">
    
    <Category name="One-liners">
      <Factor name="Conciseness">
        <Explanation>A good one-liner is short, efficient, and delivers humor in as few words as possible.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I used to play piano by ear, but now I use my hands."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I once had a dream where I was in a piano class and my teacher told me to play by ear, but I misunderstood and bent over trying to hit the keys with my head."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Punch Impact">
        <Explanation>The final word or phrase must carry a surprising or humorous twist that lands effectively.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I'm on a whiskey diet. I've lost three days already."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I'm on a salad diet. It’s green and boring, like a frog's dinner."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Linguistic Creativity">
        <Explanation>Creative use of language, such as wordplay, rhyme, or double meanings enhances impact.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Time flies like an arrow. Fruit flies like a banana."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Time flies because the clock keeps going. Bananas are fruit." </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Knock-knock jokes">
      <Factor name="Predictable Surprise">
        <Explanation>A good knock-knock joke uses a setup the audience expects but then subverts it in a playful way.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Knock knock.  
          Who's there?  
          Lettuce.  
          Lettuce who?  
          Lettuce in, it's cold out here!
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Knock knock.  
          Who’s there?  
          Banana.  
          Banana who?  
          Just banana.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Sound/Meaning Play">
        <Explanation>The joke often hinges on phonetic puns or homonyms, which must be clear and clever.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Knock knock.  
          Who's there?  
          Boo.  
          Boo who?  
          Don’t cry, it’s just a joke!
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Knock knock.  
          Who’s there?  
          Cat.  
          Cat who?  
          Cat doesn't matter.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Riddles">
      <Factor name="Cleverness">
        <Explanation>The answer should be both surprising and logically satisfying.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: What has keys but can't open locks?  
          A: A piano.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: What has teeth but doesn’t bite?  
          A: A toothbrush… but it does bite a little.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Relevance">
        <Explanation>The riddle should stay focused on the core idea; overly obscure or tangential riddles fail to land.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: What comes down but never goes up?  
          A: Rain.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: What is red and blue and green and orange and invisible?  
          A: A chameleon in a disco… maybe?
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Light bulb jokes">
      <Factor name="Stereotype Play">
        <Explanation>Uses stereotypes (often benign or exaggerated) to create relatable humor.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: How many software engineers does it take to change a light bulb?  
          A: None, that's a hardware issue.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: How many people does it take to change a light bulb?  
          A: I don't know, people do things.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Concise Build-up">
        <Explanation>The setup should be short and the punchline must flip expectations quickly.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: How many surrealists does it take to change a light bulb?  
          A: Fish.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: How many historians does it take to change a light bulb?  
          A: First you must understand the bulb’s cultural and economic context...
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Yo mama jokes">
      <Factor name="Exaggeration">
        <Explanation>Deliberate overstatement used for humorous effect.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Yo mama so old, her social security number is 1."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Yo mama is kind of older than me."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Rhythmic Delivery">
        <Explanation>These jokes tend to be funnier when they have a snappy, rhythmic delivery.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Yo mama so fat, when she skips a meal, the stock market drops."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Yo mama is fat, and when she doesn’t eat, things happen."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Anti-jokes">
      <Factor name="Deliberate Anti-climax">
        <Explanation>Humor arises from the intentional absence of a traditional punchline.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: Why did the chicken cross the road?  
          A: Because it was going to the other side.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: Why did the chicken cross the road?  
          A: Because I said so.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Deadpan Absurdity">
        <Explanation>Delivers a nonsensical or literal response in a serious tone.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Q: A man walks into a bar...  
          A: He is treated for a head injury.
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Q: A man walks into a bar...  
          A: Drinks orange juice and leaves.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Shaggy dog stories">
      <Factor name="Extended Build-up">
        <Explanation>The long, detailed setup builds anticipation for an intentionally underwhelming punchline.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          Story builds up over several minutes describing a talented dog, only to end with, "And then he died."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          Long-winded story that ends with a confusing or unrelated sentence that doesn’t subvert expectations.
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Bait-and-switch Humor">
        <Explanation>The story should lead the listener to expect a grand payoff that is intentionally silly or trivial.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>
          "...and after 10 years of searching, he finally found the rare wooly mammoth. It was stuffed. In a museum."
        </GoodExample>
        <BadExample>
          "He found the thing and was happy. The end."
        </BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Deadpan delivery">
      <Factor name="Emotionless Execution">
        <Explanation>Humor comes from saying something outrageous in a completely flat, unamused tone.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I have the body of a god. Unfortunately, it’s Buddha."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I have a god's body. It's really weird."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Contextual Contrast">
        <Explanation>The absurdity or extremity of the content contrasts with the flat tone.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I enjoy long romantic walks to the fridge."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I like to eat. Sometimes I walk too."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

  </Criteria>
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <Criteria name="Intent">

    <Category name="Satirical">
      <Factor name="Sharp Commentary">
        <Explanation>Offers a clever or insightful critique of society, politics, or culture. Adheres when it exposes truths wittily without being preachy.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"The problem with political jokes is they get elected."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Politicians are dumb and corrupt. LOL."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Topical Relevance">
        <Explanation>Targets current or culturally relevant topics. A good satirical joke needs context.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Facebook changing its name to Meta is like cigarette companies rebranding as Health Inc."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"The king should abolish taxes." (Feels dated or out-of-place)</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Wit">
        <Explanation>Relies on clever phrasing and layered meaning. Adheres when the joke contains intelligent wordplay.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Billionaires going to space proves once and for all that wealth does create distance."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Rich people are annoying."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Parody / Spoof">
      <Factor name="Style Mimicry">
        <Explanation>Accurately mimics the target’s language, structure, or tropes. Adheres when the imitation is recognizable.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"If Shakespeare wrote pizza ads: 'Dost thou hunger? Hark! Ye cheesy delight awaits!'"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Pizza is good. Shakespeare might have said so."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Exaggeration">
        <Explanation>Highlights absurd traits of the original through magnification. Works when it pushes boundaries without breaking believability.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Parody of action movies: 'He reloads his gun by screaming louder.'"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"He uses a gun. It's like an action movie."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Recognition Factor">
        <Explanation>The audience should be able to identify what is being spoofed. If it's too obscure or poorly mimicked, the joke fails.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Harry Potter fanfiction: ‘You're a wizard, Gary. Also, you're now head of HR.’"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Some guy gets powers and stuff happens."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Slapstick / Physical comedy">
      <Factor name="Visual Absurdity">
        <Explanation>Includes exaggerated, physical movement or events that are visually ridiculous. Adheres when absurdity triggers laughter from the unexpected physical behavior.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"He slipped on a banana peel, flipped mid-air, and landed in a wedding cake."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"He slipped and fell."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Timing">
        <Explanation>Precise execution of physical elements—delayed reactions, suddenness, pauses—enhances effect. Poor timing leads to awkwardness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"He waits five seconds after being hit, then slowly tips over like a tree."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"He gets hit and falls instantly—no suspense, no buildup."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Exaggeration">
        <Explanation>Goes beyond realism for comedic effect. Adheres when over-the-top action is clearly intentional and humorous.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"He fought the mosquito like it was Mortal Kombat."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"He waved the mosquito away."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Insults / Roasts">
      <Factor name="Creative Insulting">
        <Explanation>Uses originality and flair rather than generic name-calling. Adheres when insult feels fresh and clever.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"You bring everyone so much joy… when you leave the room."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"You're stupid."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Tone Balance">
        <Explanation>The insult should be funny, not hurtful. It balances edge with playfulness or affection.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Your cooking is like your Wi-Fi—sometimes it works, mostly it just burns."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"You're a terrible cook and nobody likes you."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Timing & Delivery">
        <Explanation>The roast should land at the right moment. Poor delivery can make a joke fall flat or feel forced.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"And here comes John—the only man whose haircut screams 'midlife crisis' louder than his car horn."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"John looks weird. Anyway, back to the topic."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Wholesome / Clean humor">
      <Factor name="Innocence">
        <Explanation>The joke avoids vulgarity, cruelty, or mean-spiritedness. Adheres when humor is light, kind, and inclusive.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Why did the teddy bear say no to dessert? Because it was stuffed."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Why did the grandma slap the kid? Because he was annoying."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Relatability">
        <Explanation>Evokes common shared experiences or feelings. Adheres when it connects warmly with everyday life.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Nothing says adulthood like searching for the piece of Tupperware that fits the lid."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I like sitting. That’s all."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Clever Simplicity">
        <Explanation>Simple yet smart. It avoids complexity but still surprises the audience with a smile-worthy twist.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Parallel lines have so much in common… it’s a shame they’ll never meet."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Lines don’t cross."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Dark / Gallows humor">
      <Factor name="Shock Balance">
        <Explanation>The joke uses disturbing or taboo themes, but should walk the line between edgy and offensive. Adheres when it shocks but also amuses with cleverness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I have a friend who writes songs about sewing machines. He’s a Singer-songwriter… or he was, until the accident."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Dead people are funny. LOL."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Irony / Juxtaposition">
        <Explanation>Places tragedy or horror beside the mundane or absurd for humor. Works when contrast is jarring but illuminating.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"My therapist says I have a preoccupation with vengeance. We'll see about that."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Therapists are useless."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Emotional Disarmament">
        <Explanation>Makes the dark topic emotionally palatable—often via deadpan tone, absurdity, or self-deprecation.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I told my wife I wanted to be cremated. She made me an appointment for next Thursday."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I want to die. Haha."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

  </Criteria>





	<Criteria name="Target">
	  <Category name="Dad jokes">
		<Factor name="Pun Precision">
		  <Explanation>Relies heavily on puns or wordplay. Effective when the play on words is clever and unexpected.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I'm afraid for the calendar. Its days are numbered."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"I know a joke about paper. Never mind, it's tearable."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Groan-Worthy Charm">
		  <Explanation>Delivers a pun or simple joke that causes an eye-roll, but still earns affection. Adheres when the joke is innocent yet playfully corny.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"I only know 25 letters of the alphabet. I don’t know y."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Why did the chicken cross the road? Because... chicken."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Blonde jokes">
		<Factor name="Stereotype Sensitivity">
		  <Explanation>Must tread lightly on stereotypes—acceptable when it’s exaggerated in a clearly playful and self-aware way, not degrading.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why did the blonde stare at the orange juice container? It said 'concentrate.'"</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Blondes are dumb. That’s it, that’s the joke."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Absurd Logic">
		  <Explanation>The joke should present illogical conclusions that are amusingly ridiculous. Fails when logic gaps aren’t funny or feel lazy.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"A blonde put lipstick on her forehead to make up her mind."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Blonde thought a quarterback was a refund. Haha."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Programmer / Nerd jokes">
		<Factor name="Technical Wit">
		  <Explanation>Appeals through clever use of real technical terms or logic. Works when it's true to context but simplified enough to be funny.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why do programmers prefer dark mode? Because light attracts bugs."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Code. Debug. Cry. Repeat."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Layered Understanding">
		  <Explanation>Has multiple layers of understanding—extra funny if you get the reference. Fails when it's too obscure or shallow.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"There are 10 types of people in the world: those who understand binary and those who don’t."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Segmentation fault. LOL."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Ethnic / National jokes">
		<Factor name="Cultural Cleverness">
		  <Explanation>Uses cultural traits to set up humor, ideally celebrating rather than mocking. Fails if it feels like ridicule without insight.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"In Italy, they add work to their coffee breaks. In America, we add coffee to our work breaks."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Germans have no humor. End of joke."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Friendly Universality">
		  <Explanation>Should unite across cultures, not divide—highlighting shared human quirks. Fails if it leans into outdated or mean stereotypes.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"A Brit, an American, and a Japanese guy walk into a bar... and start comparing who apologizes fastest."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Mexicans are lazy. That’s why they nap all the time. Haha."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Lawyer / Doctor / Engineer jokes">
		<Factor name="Role Reversal or Exaggeration">
		  <Explanation>Uses exaggeration or role stereotypes to invert expectations. Works when it's clever and based on known tropes.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"What’s the difference between a doctor and God? God doesn’t think he’s a doctor."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Lawyers lie. That’s funny."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Professional Logic Subversion">
		  <Explanation>Takes technical or professional logic and flips it on its head humorously. Fails when it’s just jargon or too dry.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"An engineer thinks a glass is twice as big as it needs to be."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Doctors don’t know anything. Haha."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>

	  <Category name="Gender-based humor">
		<Factor name="Playful Relatability">
		  <Explanation>Highlights differences with humor rooted in shared experience. Works when it’s light and playful, not divisive.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Why don’t women ever tell you what they want for Christmas? Because they already told you—six months ago."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Women can’t drive. LOL."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
		<Factor name="Stereotype Inversion">
		  <Explanation>Flips expected roles or comments on double standards humorously. Fails when it reinforces harm or lacks nuance.</Explanation>
		  <GoodExample>"Men are from Mars, women are from Venus. That explains why communication is so... out of this world."</GoodExample>
		  <BadExample>"Men are dumb. Period."</BadExample>
		</Factor>
	  </Category>
	</Criteria>







  <Criteria name="Culture">

    <Category name="British dry humor">
      <Factor name="Understatement">
        <Explanation>The joke deliberately minimizes or downplays an idea, emotion, or event, creating humor through contrast between delivery and implication.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"It’s just a scratch," he said, as his arm dangled by a thread.</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I'm bleeding. That’s bad."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Deadpan Delivery">
        <Explanation>Humor is enhanced by an emotionless or expressionless tone. It works when the content is absurd but the tone is serious.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I used to play piano by ear, but now I use my hands."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I’m really funny. Please laugh at this next joke."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Wit and Brevity">
        <Explanation>Smart wordplay or subtle insight conveyed succinctly. Succeeds when it's clever and concise.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"The trouble with jogging is that the ice falls out of your glass."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I once tried jogging. I didn’t like it because it was tiring and I spilled my drink and it made me feel sweaty."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Jewish humor">
      <Factor name="Self-deprecation">
        <Explanation>Makes fun of oneself or one’s identity. Works when it’s done with warmth and cleverness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I’m not a hypochondriac, I’m just very well-informed about my imminent death."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I hate myself. That’s the joke."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Existential Absurdity">
        <Explanation>Focuses on life’s paradoxes and inherent struggles, often philosophical. Effective when relatable and wry.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"God, why me? And God says, 'Because you’re annoying.'"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Life sucks and then you die. Funny, right?"</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Family and Tradition Irony">
        <Explanation>Draws on cultural expectations and subverts them gently. Works when it’s both respectful and sharp.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"My mother asked if I was warm. I said yes. She added a third sweater."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Jewish moms are crazy. Lol."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Indian PJ jokes">
      <Factor name="Pun-based Simplicity">
        <Explanation>Relies on literal and simple wordplay. Works best when clean, quick, and absurdly logical.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Why was the math book sad? Because it had too many problems."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Math book cried because it was math. Haha."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Groan-worthy Innocence">
        <Explanation>So bad it’s good—elicits a groan but also a smile due to its harmless goofiness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I told my shoes a joke. They didn’t have the sole to laugh."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"My shirt is hungry. It ate my buttons."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Predictable Surprise">
        <Explanation>Setup leads to an overly obvious punchline that’s funny because it’s exactly what you'd fear.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"What’s brown and sticky? A stick."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"What’s brown? Chocolate. LOL."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Japanese Manzai">
      <Factor name="Straightman-Clown Contrast">
        <Explanation>Relies on interplay between the serious 'tsukkomi' and the silly 'boke'. Works when the timing and energy difference land sharply.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "I bought invisible ink!" Tsukkomi: "And what do you plan to write with that—ghost letters?!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Boke: "Bananas are phones." Tsukkomi: "No they’re not."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Fast-paced Timing">
        <Explanation>Jokes rely on rapid exchanges. Works when the rhythm enhances absurdity without confusing the audience.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "I’m a genius! I put water in the toaster to boil it!" Tsukkomi: "You’re going to boil the house down!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Slow back-and-forth that drags and loses momentum.</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Situational Escalation">
        <Explanation>Starts mundane and spirals into chaos. Works when the escalation is funny and builds logically.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "Let’s dig a hole to America." Tsukkomi: "With a spoon?! You’ll hit your own feet!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Random escalation that lacks a thread: "Let’s dig to America. Then fly to Jupiter. Then explode."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="American stand-up">
      <Factor name="Relatability">
        <Explanation>The joke connects with common experiences, often in urban, everyday settings. Works when it reflects shared truths with unique perspective.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Dating in your 30s is like shopping at a thrift store. You’ll find something, but it probably has issues."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Relationships are weird. Whatever."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Observational Sharpness">
        <Explanation>Notices what others miss. Works when the insight feels fresh and cleverly worded.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Why do we press harder on the remote when the batteries are dying? Like it’s trying harder now."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Remotes are annoying."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Punchline Efficiency">
        <Explanation>Builds toward a sharp, effective payoff. Works when the setup is tight and the punchline surprises.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"My parents raised me with love and boundaries. Mostly boundaries."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"My parents were strict. That’s it."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

  </Criteria>  <Criteria name="Culture">

    <Category name="British dry humor">
      <Factor name="Understatement">
        <Explanation>The joke deliberately minimizes or downplays an idea, emotion, or event, creating humor through contrast between delivery and implication.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"It’s just a scratch," he said, as his arm dangled by a thread.</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I'm bleeding. That’s bad."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Deadpan Delivery">
        <Explanation>Humor is enhanced by an emotionless or expressionless tone. It works when the content is absurd but the tone is serious.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I used to play piano by ear, but now I use my hands."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I’m really funny. Please laugh at this next joke."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Wit and Brevity">
        <Explanation>Smart wordplay or subtle insight conveyed succinctly. Succeeds when it's clever and concise.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"The trouble with jogging is that the ice falls out of your glass."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I once tried jogging. I didn’t like it because it was tiring and I spilled my drink and it made me feel sweaty."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Jewish humor">
      <Factor name="Self-deprecation">
        <Explanation>Makes fun of oneself or one’s identity. Works when it’s done with warmth and cleverness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I’m not a hypochondriac, I’m just very well-informed about my imminent death."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"I hate myself. That’s the joke."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Existential Absurdity">
        <Explanation>Focuses on life’s paradoxes and inherent struggles, often philosophical. Effective when relatable and wry.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"God, why me? And God says, 'Because you’re annoying.'"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Life sucks and then you die. Funny, right?"</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Family and Tradition Irony">
        <Explanation>Draws on cultural expectations and subverts them gently. Works when it’s both respectful and sharp.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"My mother asked if I was warm. I said yes. She added a third sweater."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Jewish moms are crazy. Lol."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Indian PJ jokes">
      <Factor name="Pun-based Simplicity">
        <Explanation>Relies on literal and simple wordplay. Works best when clean, quick, and absurdly logical.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Why was the math book sad? Because it had too many problems."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Math book cried because it was math. Haha."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Groan-worthy Innocence">
        <Explanation>So bad it’s good—elicits a groan but also a smile due to its harmless goofiness.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"I told my shoes a joke. They didn’t have the sole to laugh."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"My shirt is hungry. It ate my buttons."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Predictable Surprise">
        <Explanation>Setup leads to an overly obvious punchline that’s funny because it’s exactly what you'd fear.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"What’s brown and sticky? A stick."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"What’s brown? Chocolate. LOL."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="Japanese Manzai">
      <Factor name="Straightman-Clown Contrast">
        <Explanation>Relies on interplay between the serious 'tsukkomi' and the silly 'boke'. Works when the timing and energy difference land sharply.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "I bought invisible ink!" Tsukkomi: "And what do you plan to write with that—ghost letters?!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Boke: "Bananas are phones." Tsukkomi: "No they’re not."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Fast-paced Timing">
        <Explanation>Jokes rely on rapid exchanges. Works when the rhythm enhances absurdity without confusing the audience.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "I’m a genius! I put water in the toaster to boil it!" Tsukkomi: "You’re going to boil the house down!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Slow back-and-forth that drags and loses momentum.</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Situational Escalation">
        <Explanation>Starts mundane and spirals into chaos. Works when the escalation is funny and builds logically.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>Boke: "Let’s dig a hole to America." Tsukkomi: "With a spoon?! You’ll hit your own feet!"</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>Random escalation that lacks a thread: "Let’s dig to America. Then fly to Jupiter. Then explode."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

    <Category name="American stand-up">
      <Factor name="Relatability">
        <Explanation>The joke connects with common experiences, often in urban, everyday settings. Works when it reflects shared truths with unique perspective.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Dating in your 30s is like shopping at a thrift store. You’ll find something, but it probably has issues."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Relationships are weird. Whatever."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Observational Sharpness">
        <Explanation>Notices what others miss. Works when the insight feels fresh and cleverly worded.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"Why do we press harder on the remote when the batteries are dying? Like it’s trying harder now."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"Remotes are annoying."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
      <Factor name="Punchline Efficiency">
        <Explanation>Builds toward a sharp, effective payoff. Works when the setup is tight and the punchline surprises.</Explanation>
        <GoodExample>"My parents raised me with love and boundaries. Mostly boundaries."</GoodExample>
        <BadExample>"My parents were strict. That’s it."</BadExample>
      </Factor>
    </Category>

  </Criteria>
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <Criteria name="Modern / Internet">
  <Category name="Memes">
    <Factor name="Template Innovation">
      <Explanation>Uses a familiar meme format but brings a fresh twist or creative subversion. Adheres when the joke surprises while fitting the format.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>Image: Distracted Boyfriend. Labels: "Me" looking at "well-written joke" while ignoring "recycled punchline".</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>Image: Drake meme with reused "No/Yes" joke from 2016 without any change.</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Cultural Referencing">
      <Explanation>Effective use of pop culture or current events that resonate widely. Fails when the reference is outdated or too niche.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"When you realize ChatGPT just became self-aware and starts correcting *your* grammar."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"When you realize Windows Vista was bad." (Too outdated)</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Visual Humor Sync">
      <Explanation>Image and caption work together, enhancing each other. Lacks impact when the image and text feel mismatched.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>Image: Dog in a suit with caption: “When you accidentally send your resume to a meme page.”</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>Image: Random cat. Caption: "I love quantum physics."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
  </Category>

  <Category name="Dad joke bots / AI-generated">
    <Factor name="Punniness">
      <Explanation>Relies on groan-worthy, clean puns. Works when it's silly but clever; fails when it's too obvious or strained.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"Why did the scarecrow win an award? Because he was outstanding in his field."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"I like bread. It’s loaf-ly."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Simplicity">
      <Explanation>Joke should be easy to understand, quick to get. Breaks down if it requires explanation or overthinking.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"I'm on a seafood diet. I see food and I eat it."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"Time is a flat lasagna, just like my uncle said when..." (Too convoluted)</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Wholesomeness">
      <Explanation>Should be light-hearted and family-safe. Misses the mark if it's mean-spirited or edgy.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"What do you call fake spaghetti? An impasta."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"I’d tell you a dirty joke, but I showered."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
  </Category>

  <Category name="Twitter / Reddit-style jokes">
    <Factor name="Relatable Specificity">
      <Explanation>Joke uses highly specific scenarios people can deeply relate to. Fails when too generic or vague.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"Me: *tries to sleep* Brain: Top 10 most embarrassing moments from 2006."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"Sometimes I get tired."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Brevity with Punch">
      <Explanation>Condenses humor into a compact, witty statement. Too long = loses effect; too short = unclear.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"Dating me is like software updates: mostly ignored until it’s too late."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"I once had a thought about relationships and software that I think is kind of funny and maybe relevant..."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Tone Consistency">
      <Explanation>Voice should feel authentic and match the joke's style. Bad when the tone shifts mid-joke.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>"I didn't get the job, but I did learn how to cry silently in a public bathroom. So, growth."</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>"I was sad so I baked cookies and then I thought about nihilism and that was weird."</BadExample>
    </Factor>
  </Category>

  <Category name="TikTok punchlines / Vine-style shorts">
    <Factor name="Timing and Delivery">
      <Explanation>The humor relies on perfect timing, fast cuts, or sudden twists. Loses impact if pacing drags or punchline is predictable.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>Video cuts from guy saying “I’m totally fine” to him immediately falling through a chair.</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>Setup drags for 30 seconds and punchline is “I spilled coffee.”</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Reaction Layering">
      <Explanation>Incorporates reactions (real or exaggerated) as part of the humor. Fails when reactions feel forced or mismatched.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>Girl says “I hate surprises” and roommate bursts in dressed as a cake; both scream.</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>Guy says something mildly funny, then forces laugh track over it.</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Unexpected Escalation">
      <Explanation>Joke intensifies quickly in an absurd or exaggerated way. Doesn’t work if the escalation is random or lacks buildup.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>Starts with “I just need one egg” and ends with the kitchen on fire.</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>Starts with “I just need one egg” and cuts to outer space with no connection.</BadExample>
    </Factor>
  </Category>

  <Category name="Shitposts / Absurd Gen-Z humor">
    <Factor name="Embrace of Nonsense">
      <Explanation>Deliberate absurdity, randomness, or anti-humor. Works when chaos feels intentional; fails if it's just incoherent.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>“me: *breathes* cereal box in the distance: YOU HAVE AWAKENED THE ANCIENT CURSE”</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>“me banana car loud funny smell zzz lol”</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Meta-awareness">
      <Explanation>Breaks the fourth wall or mocks the format of jokes/memes themselves. Fails when it tries too hard or lacks substance.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>“This is a meme. The joke is missing. That’s the joke.”</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>“Haha look I said meme. Is funny yet?”</BadExample>
    </Factor>
    <Factor name="Contradiction Play">
      <Explanation>Combines things that logically shouldn’t go together for surreal effect. Fails when it just confuses without payoff.</Explanation>
      <GoodExample>“I put my hopes and dreams in the microwave. Now it’s beeping.”</GoodExample>
      <BadExample>“Toothpaste is politics if you think about it.”</BadExample>
    </Factor>
  </Category>
</Criteria>
